How does one come to know the unknowable?
人要如何得知未知的事?
"What faculties must a man possess?
人必须拥有何种能力?
"Since it was discovered that whale oil could light our cities in ways never achieved before,
自从发现鲸油 能以空前未有的方式照亮城市
"it created global demand.
全球需求随之而起
"It has pushed man to venture further and further
迫使人类冒着愈来愈大的风险
"into the deep blue unknown.
进入未知的海域
"We know not its depths,
大海深不可测
"nor the host of creatures that live there.
也有多不胜数的生物
"Monsters.
怪物
"Are they real?
它们是真实的吗?
"Or do the stories exist only to make us respect the sea's dark secrets?
或者那些故事的存在 只是让人类尊重大海的神秘
"The question both vexes and excites me
这个问题令我困惑又兴奋
"and is the reason I've written you a second time to request a meeting.
因此我再度写信要求见您
"A conversation with you, sir, I believe will serve me well for the novel I intend to write,
与您对谈想必会使 我着手要写的小说获益良多
"currently entitled Moby Dick.
目前书名暂订为"白鲸记"
"I hope you will reconsider my offer.
希望您能重新考虑我的提议
"The unknown.
未知
"That is where my imagination yearns to venture.
是我的想像力渴望探索之处
"And so the question plagues me still.
所以困扰我的问题依旧
"How does a man come to know the unknowable?
人要如何得知未知的事?
"Sincerely, Herman Melville."
敬启 赫尔曼梅尔维尔
We're closed.
我们打烊了
No boarders after 8:00.
8点之后不提供住宿
You came.
你来了
Someone here for you, my love.
亲爱的 你有客人
Tom Nickerson?
汤姆尼可森?
Herman Melville.
赫尔曼梅尔维尔
We received your letter.
我们收到你的信
You're either a desperate man or a fool to come all the way to Nantucket.
你一定是无可救药或愚不可及 才会专程来南塔克岛
Well, my offer still stands.
我的提议仍有效
Three months' lodgings for a single night's talk.
三个月的住宿费换一晚的谈话
All I have in the world.
那是我的所有财产了
But I prefer to think of it as an investment.
但我宁可想成投资
I want you to tell me what happened to the Essex.
我想请教艾塞克斯号发生什么事
What do you think happened?
你觉得呢?
There are rumblings.
有一些传闻
- Rumors that the Essex was... - What do you want?
- 据说艾塞克斯号... - 你想怎样?
What story do you expect to hear?
你指望听到什么?
That of the whale.
那只鲸鱼
The Essex ran aground. There was a full inquiry.
艾塞克斯号触礁 调查结案了
I believe the inquiry was less than truthful.
我不相信调查结果是真相
Get out.
出去
You are the last survivor of the Essex, sir.
你是仅存的艾塞克斯号生还者
If you won't talk, who will?
如果你不说 谁会说?
Did you not hear me?
你聋了吗?
Leave. Now.
马上就滚
- No. You mustn't go. Please. - He is in no mind to talk.
- 不 拜托别走 - 他不愿意谈话
And I haven't come all this way to be humiliated and waste my time.
我不是专程来受辱和浪费时间
Please, Mr. Melville.
拜托 梅尔维尔先生
He won't talk about the Essex to me.
他不愿对我和任何人谈起此事
To anyone. Never has. Never.
从来没有 从不
There's an agony about him.
他痛苦不堪
His soul
他的心灵
is in torment,
深受折磨
and in need of confession.
需要告解
Please, just let me talk to him. Please.
拜托 让我劝劝他
Love.
亲爱的
I believe it would do you good to talk to the man.
我相信跟他谈谈对你有益
No.
免谈
You listen well.
你给我听好
Who holds this place together while you drink yourself to death?
你发酒疯时是谁维持这个家?
You will talk with this man as much as is necessary to keep the money.
你得跟他谈 也有必要收下钱
You know our circumstances, Thomas.
你懂我们的处境 汤玛斯
Only as much as is necessary.
我只会点到为止
I'll get whiskey.
我去拿威士忌
I neglected to mention it in my letter, but I was a whaler once.
我在信里忘了提 但我也曾是猎鲸人
One trip, I mean.
只出航一次
Green hand.
嫩手
So, you've seen it all.
那你都见识过了
My wife read your books.
内人读了你的书
She enjoyed them.
她很喜欢
I'm happy to hear it.
我很高兴听到
I've had good sales.
我的书卖得不错
And I think this story
我想这个故事
could surpass the success of even my first novel,
可能超越我的第一本小说
which did quite well.
那本相当畅销
Another of your seafaring yarns?
你又想出一本航海奇谈?
Have you read Hawthorne, Mr. Melville?
你读过霍桑的书吗?
Now there's a writer.
那才算作家
Great writer.
伟大的作家
He is.
确实
But he is not here. And I am.
但他不在这里 而我来了
For my own particular reasons.
为了我个人的特殊理由
I will tell you of the Essex.
我会告诉你艾塞克斯号的事
I believe you will be disappointed.
我相信你会很失望
But every word I say will be true.
但我的一言一语绝对真实
Story of the Essex
艾塞克斯号的故事
is the story of two men.
是两个人的故事
Captain George Pollard
船长乔治波拉德
and his first mate,
以及他的大副
Owen Chase.
欧文契斯
Owen.
欧文
You don't wanna be late.
可别迟到了
I'll be there.
我会准时的
Besides, can't have our daughter sleeping under a leaky roof, can we?
总不能让女儿睡在漏水屋檐下吧
What makes you so sure it's a girl?
你怎么确定是女儿?
Well, it has to be.
非女儿不可
So she can remind me why I still love you when you're being stubborn.
才能提醒我为何仍爱着倔强的你
Well, if it's to be a daughter, she'll be a version of you, not me.
女儿的话会像你 不是我
Blond locks and determined to conquer the world.
一头金发 决心征服世界
I suppose after today, you'll be trading in that tunic for a uniform.
今天之后你会换上船长制服吧
That's right. Finally out of this patch of dirt, into a captain's house like you deserve.
没错 终于能从茅屋 换到你才该住的船长豪宅
I don't need one of those houses in town with stuffy neighbors.
我不必搬进城跟古板人家为邻
There's plenty of room here for the three of us.
这间房子够我们三人住
You know, sometimes your kind heart and good nature
有时你的好心和善良
is just unbearable.
令人招架不住
Go get your captaincy.
去领你的船长头衔吧
- What's your bid? - I'll have $1.90.
- 你出价多少? - 1.9
- I've got 1,000 gallons at $2! - I'll take 40 shares!
- 已经有人出价2元 - 我买40股
Seller! Seller! Over here!
卖家 这里喊价
Criterion's back with a fine haul. 1,600 barrels.
标准号丰收而返 1600桶
A new record. 50 pounds sterling for head matter on the London market.
刷新纪录 伦敦市场的鲸蜡涨到50英磅
Congratulations.
恭喜
- Good morning, Mr. Chase. - Mr. Mason.
- 早安 契斯先生 - 梅森先生
Come in, please.
请进
My partner, Benjamin Fuller.
我的合伙人班杰明福勒
Good morning, sir.
早安 先生
Do sit down.
请坐
Mr. Chase.
契斯先生
I do hope you realize how satisfied we are
希望你了解我们十分满意
with the work you've done for us over the years.
过去几年你为我们的贡献
Thank you, sir.
谢谢 先生
Now, one of our ships, the Essex,
我们其中一艘船 艾塞克斯号
has just been refitted at great expense and is to go to sea.
刚花大钱整修 准备出海
Now, having made such an investment in her, we want to be sure she's in the best possible hands.
既然所费不赀 我们一定要把它交给顶尖能手
So,
所以
it gives us great pleasure to offer you a position aboard her.
我们很乐意提供你船上的职位
As first mate.
做为大副
As first mate?
大副?
Mr. Mason, you promised me command of a ship after my last voyage
梅森先生 上次返航 你承诺让我当船长
when I brought you back 1,500 barrels. Do you remember? You gave me your word.
我为您带回1500桶 记得吗? 你向我保证过
That promise must now be deferred.
那个保证必须延期了
Like everyone else, we've had a lean time recently.
时机歹歹 我们最近获利不佳
No, never on my watch.
由我监督就不会
Nantucket now dominates the world market.
南塔克岛已主宰全球市场
That must not change.
这是不可改变的事实
This is no time for experimentation.
没有试用时间了
The Essex will be captained by George Pollard,
艾塞克斯号的船长是乔治波拉德
scion of a great whaling family.
伟大捕鲸家族的后裔
His father also happens to be our patron.
他父亲恰好也是我们的赞助人
Blood, Mr. Chase.
血统很重要 契斯先生
You can have all the voyages under your belt you want,
你的航行成就不同凡响
but blood will always win out.
但血统始终会胜出
Yes, well, blood is not gonna fill a ship with oil, Mr. Mason.
对 但血统不会让你满载而归
To successfully command, a captain needs respect. Now, what if the men don't respect him?
船长要服得了人 才能成功指挥 要是水手不服他呢?
You will make sure that they do.
你要确保他们服从他
Ah, good day, gentlemen.
再见 各位
I understand your disappointment,
我了解你的失望 那么...
so, a one-fifteenth lay.
15分之1的分红
That's more than I've ever paid any first officer.
这是我给过大副最高的价码
And if you bring back 2,000 barrels of oil, I give you my word,
只要带回2000桶鲸油 我向你保证...
next time, you will have your captaincy.
下次你会当上船长
You've given me your word before, Mr. Mason.
你早就向我保证过 梅森先生
No, this time, I'll take it in writing.
这次我要白纸黑字
Captain Pollard.
波拉德船长
We've just had a most agreeable conversation with Mr. Chase.
我们刚跟契斯先生相谈甚欢
He'll be honored to serve under you.
他会很荣幸当你的大副
I'm glad to hear it.
我很庆幸听到
Now I'm to babysit a greenhorn.
居然要我当个嫩手的褓姆
Some chinless Nantucketer born with a damn silver spoon in his mouth.
含金汤匙出生的没种南塔克岛人
You know, I should've thrown the offer back in their faces.
我应该把合同丢回他们脸上
Why? You now have the offer of command in writing.
为什么? 你这次有书面保证了
Yes, well, a liar's word is worthless, even on paper.
是咧 骗子的话不可信 就算有书面也是
You know, I'd love you just as much if you were a merchant captain.
就算你是商船船长 我会同样爱你
And you wouldn't be gone for two years.
你也不会一去就是2年
I won't be gone two years.
我不会去到2年
A Bedford whaler came back last week who was gone three.
贝特福特的捕鲸船出去3年 上周才回来
She lost two men and still with her hull half empty.
两人罹难 收获量才一半
Yeah, well, they were from Bedford, and they didn't have me on board.
那是贝特福特人 可惜他们没找我
Son of a bitch!
王八蛋
I will captain my own ship!
我要指挥自己的船
A whaling ship.
捕鲸船
Up to them, all we'd ever have is this patch of dirt, and that's not gonna happen, Peggy.
靠他们 我们永远只能住茅屋 门都没有 佩姬
Those are your father's words, not yours.
你只是重复你爸的话
What's wrong with his words?
他的话有错吗?
He wanted things for his family, for himself.
他是为了家人和自己
He was a dreamer, Owen.
他是梦想家 欧文
Yes, he was.
没错
Dreamed of the sea and never got to sail it because of men like them.
梦想海洋 却被那些烂人限制出海
At least he got to see his children born.
至少他看得到孩子出生
It's all I know.
捕鲸是我唯一擅长的
I'm sorry.
抱歉
I married a whaleman.
我嫁给猎鲸人
Hey.
听着
I'll come back as quick as a summer's night, I swear.
我会尽快回来 我发誓
Just come back.
要平安回来
Promise me.
向我保证
I already swore to you. Now you want me to promise, too?
我已经发誓 还得向你保证?
I promise.
我保证
Son, a word With you.
孩子 借一步说话
To be a captain, you cannot be a friend.
当船长就不能当朋友
You are their superior.
你是他们的上司
Never forget that. Never let them forget that.
千万别忘记这点 也别让他们忘记
Thank you, sir.
谢谢 先生
Your great-grandfather and a few others created this industry.
你曾祖父和几个伙伴创立捕鲸业
Without us, without you, the world plunges into darkness.
没有我们 没有你 世界就会黯淡无光
I hope to bring honor to the Pollard family name, sir.
我希望为波拉德家族带来荣耀
"Thou didst, O Lord, create the mighty whale
主啊 祢创造了巨鲸
"That wondrous monster of a mighty length
那般雄伟颀长的巨怪
"Beyond conception his unmeasured strength
无以忖度那无穷的力量
"But, everlasting God, thou dost ordain
但永存的上帝 在祢的定夺之下
"That we, poor feeble mortals should engage
我们软弱的凡人该竭尽全力
"Ourselves, our wives and children to maintain
为自己和妻小谋生
"This dreadful monster with a martial rage"
以英勇的盛怒抵抗这可怕怪物
O Father, grant that your glorious light shine on these men.
天父 赐予祢的荣光照耀这些人
Ensure them a prosperous voyage,
担保他们旅途丰收
that they may return safely and with a full ship,
平安返乡 满载而归
so that the white flames of Nantucket whale oil
使南塔克鲸油的白焰
may continue to keep light in our homes,
能继续照亮我们的家和街道
city streets safe from sin in the night,
免于夜晚的罪恶
and to fuel the machines of industry
并供给工业机械的燃料
that drive our great nation forward
以推动伟大祖国的进步
as our noble species evolves.
跟上吾国高贵人种的进化
In your name, we pray.
我们以主之名祈祷
So,
那么
what month was this?
当时是几月?
Late in the year.
年底
We were one of the last ships to go out,
我们是最后出航的船
which is why my friend Barzillai and I got a berth.
所以我和我朋友巴齐莱 才能上船工作
You know,
那时...
I was 14. Fourteen.
我当时才14岁 14岁呢
Nickerson, you're standing around, boy. Move!
尼可森 别闲晃了 快干活
First time to sea. Scared,
第一次出海
but more scared to show it.
很害怕 但更害怕泄露出惊恐
Barzillai was 17.
巴齐莱17岁
Orphans. Grew up on the wharf.
孤儿 在码头长大
Both in a hurry to be called men.
我们俩都急着想长大成人
Grubs, what are those pins they're wearing?
伙伴 他们戴的饰针是什么?
They're whale pins, Thomas.
是猎鲸饰针 汤玛斯
How do I get one of them?
怎样才会有?
Well, you gotta thrust the killing lance
你要用矛枪刺死...
Into the largest beast that ever breathed on this Earth.
地球有史以来最大的野兽
Nickerson, get the green stuff to Mr. Bond, there.
尼可森 把蔬菜拿给邦德先生
Make it quick, damn it.
还不快去
I shall have 12 of those one day.
总有一天我会有12个饰针
Windlass is ready and sails are loose, sir.
绞盘准备好了 帆也松开了
Mr. Joy, this is only half my order!
乔伊先生 这只是我订的一半
Put them over the ground tier casks.
放在底层水桶上
Well, well, you being on board means only one thing.
你上船只代表一件事
Yeah, at least there's one person on this ship who knows the truth about Owen Chase.
代表船上有人知道 欧文契斯的底细
No, that all the other ships have already crewed up.
不 其他船都已经找齐人手
Now, now. I'm a reformed man, Owen.
好样的 我改掉恶习了 欧文
Question is, are you?
问题是 你呢?
Don't tell me Matthew Joy's put down the bottle.
别唬我马修乔伊戒酒了
Dry as sand.
滴酒不沾
Has Owen Chase put down his temper?
那欧文契斯改掉坏脾气了?
Ah, serene as the church.
平心静气
I'll believe that when I see it.
眼见为凭
And given our captain,
瞧谁是船长
I'll give your serenity about
我猜你的平静会维持...
48 hours?
48小时?
Good luck.
祝好运
Pollard. George Pollard.
波拉德 乔治波拉德
Owen Chase.
欧文契斯
"Chase." That's an off-island name, isn't it?
契斯 是离岛姓氏吧?
Yes, it is.
是的
And very shortly, we will be off-island for some time, and I'll be very much at home.
很快我们会离岛一阵子 我就会逍遥自在
Must say I was surprised.
我承认我有点惊讶
Normally, a captain gets to choose his first mate.
通常船长可以选择他的大副
An experienced captain, yes.
有经验的船长是可以
you can understand from the owners' point of view, they want to feel their investment's in the hands of men.
当然从业主的观点不难理解 他们想把投资交给能手
Indeed.
确实
They probably want a little extra reassurance, that's all.
他们可能想要多点保险罢了
Well, do keep an eye on me and let me know if I'm doing anything wrong.
那有劳关照 我出错说一声
Oh, I know no other way, Captain.
只能这样罗 船长
Mr. Chase, haul short the anchor.
契斯先生 拉起船锚
Yank to the wind! There's topmen aloft.
前桅迎风 桅顶起帆
- Aye! - Mr. Lawrence, take the helm. - Aye, sir.
- 劳伦斯先生 你掌舵 - 是
Mr. Joy, make sail.
乔伊先生 扬帆起航
Mr. Cole! Mr. Chappel! Stand by the spanker.
柯勒 查普尔 后桅纵帆旁待命
Set your fore staysail and your fore and main topsails.
张开前支索帆及前桅和主桅上帆
- Come on, look lively, you lads. - Come on, Nickerson!
- 大伙儿打起精神 - 加油 尼可森 动作快一点
While we're young! Let fall clews and bunts and sheet ho!
解开所有缆绳 放下风帆
Set topsails and topgallants. Heave away on the windlass.
张开上桅帆和上层帆 卷起绞盘
Heave away on the windlass.
卷起绞盘
Set topgallants. Let go clew lines and sheet ho!
张开上层帆 解开缆绳 放下风帆
There's a snarl in the gasket, sir.
束帆索打结了
Mr. Chappel, take the helm.
查普尔先生 你掌舵
It won't clear, Mr. Chase!
解不开 契斯先生
Come on! Why aren't those braces laid out?
快点 为什么绳索还没放好?
- Mr. Ray, where are my headsails? - Aye, sir!
- 雷伊先生 前桅帆怎么没张开? - 遵命
Crank away on the windlass!
转动绞盘
Crank away on the windlass, sir!
快卷起绞盘
Nickerson, pull!
尼可森 用力拉
Make sail, God damn it!
扬帆起航 该死
God and all of Nantucket is watching, men.
天啊 全南塔克人都在看
Anchor's trim!
船锚平衡了
Captain! Head down!
船长 低头
Mind your head, Captain.
小心头 船长
What's the matter, Mr. Sheppard?
西帕德先生 怎么了?
Gasket's fouled the sheet, sir.
束帆索缠住风帆
It won't clear, Mr. Chase!
解不开 契斯先生
Topgallant sheet is jammed!
上层帆卡住了
The gasket still won't clear!
束帆索还是解不开
We don't have enough sail on yet.
帆还开得不够
Still won't clear!
还是解不开
Watch your step!
小心脚步
It's the gasket, Owen!
束帆索缠住了 欧文
Stand clear.
让开
Whoa! Bloody hell!
天啊 搞定了
Let fall your course!
放下风帆
Heave!
拉起
Make fast!
拉紧
Nice piece of work, Mr. Chase.
干得好 契斯先生
If we make Cape Verdes in the next two weeks, we'll have a decent chance of reaching the Pacific on schedule.
若2周能到维德角 我们就很有机会准时抵达太平洋
Corn, Mr. Chase?
契斯先生 来点玉米?
Oh, no, thank you, sir. Never did have much of a taste for it.
不 谢了 玉米不合我的胃口
That's odd.
那可怪了
Told your father grew corn on Cape Cod.
听说令尊在鳕鱼角种过玉米
That's right. He did.
没错
As you can imagine, I certainly grew tired of eating it every day.
那你就知道 我每天吃当然腻了
Corn. Okra. Beans, I believe?
玉米 秋葵 想必还有豆子?
Before he went to jail.
在他入狱之前
Are you familiar with this story, Mr. Joy?
乔伊先生 你熟悉这些事?
Sir?
先生?
Were you aware that
你知道...
Mr. Chase was effectively orphaned due to his father's incarceration?
契斯先生的父亲坐牢 所以他跟孤儿没两样?
Well, we all have our own paths to sea.
这个嘛 我们各有出海的理由
As a rule, we tend not to ask too many questions.
通常我们不会多问
Hmm. Can't have been easy, though. Yet
这可不容易 好在...
you had Nantucket's great seafaring family to adopt you.
有南塔克岛的航海大家庭收留你
This is far from the first time I've been called a landsman or an off-islander
这早就不是第一次 南塔克人叫我内陆人或离岛人
by some Nantucketer, reminding me how I am not a part of that family.
提醒我不是那个大家庭的一员
Now, if the Captain will excuse me, there are whaleboats and watches to assign.
船长 恕我失陪 我要去分配捕鲸艇和值班了
No, sir. Not for me.
不 先生 我不喝
- Not a drop? - No, sir.
- 滴酒不沾? - 对 先生
Like I said,
如我所说
sometimes the fewer questions one asks, the better.
有时少问为妙
Serve that food up.
上菜
Getting this slop on the first day?
第一天就吃这么烂?
Cheap bastards. Where's the meat?
小气鬼 肉在哪里?
That's a gorgeous girl, Mr. Chappel.
西帕德先生 这小妞很正
A vision of beauty, that. Carved on a varnished whale bone.
把我的女神刻在鲸骨上
- Let me have a touch. - Don't touch.
- 我摸一下 - 别乱摸
I thought you were married, anyway.
反正你都结婚了
I am, and there she is.
对 就是她
Well, that's her nose, anyway.
其实只有鼻子像她
Congratulations, ladies.
恭喜 娘子军
That was a fine job trimming sails today.
今天出航还真顺利
A sorrier pack of deck wallopers I don't think I've ever seen.
我从没见过这么逊的船队
Mr. Chappel.
查普尔先生
Sir!
先生
You're Captain's harpooner.
你是船长的鲸叉手
Mr. Lawrence, you'll be mine.
劳伦斯先生 你是我的鲸叉手
Aye, sir.
遵命
And Mr. Peterson.
彼得森先生
Second mate's harpooner.
二副的鲸叉手
Aye, sir.
遵命
There'll be six men to a boat.
一艘小艇6人
First drills are tomorrow. Six bells sharp.
明天第一次训练 7点整
We're not even east of Halifax, sir.
我们连哈利法克斯东部都没到
What's your name?
报上名字
Coffin. Henry Coffin.
柯芬 亨利柯芬
He's the Captain's cousin, sir.
他是船长的表弟
Well, well, Mr. Coffin.
那好 柯芬先生
You think a whale knows if it's east of Halifax?
你以为鲸鱼认得哈利法克斯东部?
I don't know who all of you are or how you got here.
我不了你们什么来头 或怎么上船的
Some of you probably have felonies to hide and you're on the run.
有些人可能犯了重罪在逃
That's fine. I don't give a damn.
无所谓 我不在乎
But in return, you exist for one thing
但作为回报 你只有一个目的
and one thing only.
唯一的目的
And that is whale oil.
那就是鲸油
I intend to fill our 2,000 barrels and be home as quickly as possible.
我打算装满2000桶 尽快回家
And even when the weather is fine and there are no whales, Mr. Coffin,
柯芬先生 甚至天气好没鲸鱼时
we will lower the boats and practice all maneuvers
我们还是会放下小艇
necessary in the capture of a whale.
练习捕鲸必备的所有技巧
And any man who is idle will find himself swimming home. Is that understood?
谁偷懒就自己游回家 了了没?
Aye, sir.
先生
Greenhorn.
嫩手
On deck.
上甲板
On you go.
去吧
Aye, aye, landsman.
是咧 内陆人
- Thomas Nickerson, right? - Aye, sir.
- 汤玛斯尼可森 是吧? - 是 先生
You know, some feel sick at first.
有些人一开始会想吐
Please, pull me back up!
拜托拉我上去
Best way to square it with King Neptune, boy!
这是适应大海的最好方式
Please bring me up!
拜托让我上去
Better now?
好多了?
Ah, shit.
好恶
Sir, I am so sorry.
先生 很抱歉
Well, now you got something to write home to your mother about.
现在你可有东西写信跟老妈说了
My mother's buried up in Smith's Hill.
我妈埋在史密斯丘
There's a stone for my father, too.
我爸的墓碑也在那里
He was lost at sea before I was born.
他在我出生前在海上失踪
Here, give me that.
那个给我
Well, this is your family now, boy.
这是你的家庭了 孩子
For better or for worse.
不论好坏
Worse, mostly.
大多是坏的
Swab the deck, kid.
甲板擦干净 小鬼
Dogwatch! You're gonna learn what it takes to be Whalers today, mates.
轮值 今天你们会学到 当猎鲸人的本事
Aye, sir!
遵命
- You led that line wrong, Nickerson. - Aye, sir.
- 放错绳索了 尼可森 - 知道了
- We'll stay at this till sundown if we have to. - Aye, Mr. Joy, sir!
- 再犯错就练到天黑 - 是 乔伊先生
Main topsail leech lines!
主桅上帆的起帆索
Harpooner, make ready to boat!
鲸叉手 准备登艇
- Aye, sir! - Aye, Mr. Joy!
- 遵命 - 是 乔伊先生
Go main topsail leech lines. Too slow, you damn coofs!
拉紧主桅上帆的起帆索 太慢了 内地人
The bailing piggins.
舀水桶
You will learn every inch of this ship before you return to your bunks.
对这艘船了若指掌才能回去睡觉
Sweat that line, Barz.
用力拉绳 巴齐
- You need to move quicker, Mr. Ray. - Aye, Mr. Chase.
- 动作加快 雷伊先生 - 是 契斯先生
Ain't no greenhorns no more, Mr. Chase.
我不再是嫩手了 契斯先生
You're a sailor now!
你是水手了
Not bad, Mr. Ray. Well done.
不错 雷伊先生 表现很好
Forecourse bunts!
前桅帆中部
Get used to it, lads. You're gonna work like horses.
习惯就好 你们会被操得很凶
Mr. Chase?
契斯先生
Sir.
船长
Set stunsails.
张开副帆
Is that wise, sir? We're nearing the Gulf Stream. Best keep it five knots till we can see the weather.
那样好吗? 我们正接近墨西哥湾流 搞清楚天气前最好保持五节
We are two days behind.
我们落后2天了
We need to make up the time if we're to catch the easterlies.
我们要加快进度才赶得上东风
Set stunsails.
张开副帆
- Set stunsails. Come on, move. - Aye, Mr. Chase!
- 张开副帆 赶快 - 是 契斯先生
Belay that! Set stunsails!
拴住绳索 张开副帆
Get aloft, Mr. Coffin. The captain wants speed.
柯芬先生 到桅顶 船长要加速
Look for braces, lads. Trim for speed.
注意绳索 调整速度
Set fore the main topsail and topgallant stunsails, men. Move it.
主桅上帆和上层副帆向前 赶快
Make fast your stunsail halyard.
拉紧副帆吊索
Make fast stunsail halyard, sir.
拉紧副帆吊索 先生
Stunsail boom ready, sir!
副帆杠准备好了
Bracing fore topsail, sir.
系紧上桅帆
Hey!
好耶
- The captain's got us moving now! - We're finally getting somewhere!
- 船长让我们变快了 - 终于有进展了
She may be old, but she can still roll, boys!
这艘船有点年纪 但仍冲劲十足
Sir, a squall on the starboard bow. We must shorten sail immediately.
船长 右舷船头有暴风 我们该立刻收帆减速
Not just yet, Mr. Chase.
还不必 契斯先生
Sir, we are headed into a squall at more than 8 knots, and it's moving faster than that.
船长 八节速度驶向暴风太快了
Let it come. The men are soft from months on land. They need a good baptism. Let them know our work has begun.
没啥好怕 船员在陆地安逸太久 他们需要震憾教育 才能展开任务
If we don't shorten sail and bear off, it'll catch us on the beam.
若不减速和转向 船侧会受到冲击
Mr. Chase,
契斯先生
we will stand on.
我们会勇往直前
Mr. Lawrence? Hold our course.
劳伦斯先生 方向不变
Holding course, sir.
方向不变 船长
We'll lose half a day running like that. We'll skirt the edge of it.
若避开会拖延半天 我们会绕过暴风边缘
If the men can't handle a gust like this, then God help us all.
如果船员搞不定这种阵风 那就听天由命了
Best secure for heavy weather.
准备好迎向狂风暴雨
Rough weather coming up, boys. Get this deck secure.
接近暴风雨 稳住甲板
Double gripes on the boats!
小艇系上双层扣带
Best prepare for weather, Mr. Bond. We're headed into a squall.
准备好面对恶劣天气 邦德先生 我们正朝向暴风
Secure the main hatch!
关紧主舱
She's moving fast!
船速太快了
We must fall off and run with it.
我们必须转向且顺风而行
We will stand on, Mr. Chase.
继续前进 契斯先生
Mr. Lawrence! Hold your course.
劳伦斯先生 方向不变
Holding course, sir.
方向不变
Sea's coming aboard!
海水涌入
Hold on!
抓稳了
Shorten sail, Mr. Chase!
收帆减速 契斯先生
Climb to weather and grab the shrouds!
沿着暴风 抓着支索
Climb to weather! Get to windward and hold on!
船侧迎风 撑住
We need to get those sails down!
我们要放下风帆
Go lee!
往背风处
Nickerson, hold fast!
尼可森 抓紧
Hold steady lines!
抓紧绳索
Hold fast!
抓紧
Turn the ship! Turn to leeward!
转舵 转向背风
No! The damage is done!
不 已经来不及了
- Strike topgallants. Let fly sheets! - No, turn the ship!
- 张开上层帆 让风帆鼓起 - 不 转舵
Veer off, Mr. Lawrence.
转向 劳伦斯先生
It's too late! It's too goddamn late!
太迟了 为时已晚
- We'll be broadsided! - Turn this ship!
- 会冲击到船侧 - 转舵
- Hold on! - Turn!
- 撑住 - 转向
Strike those damn topgallants!
快张开上层帆
Hold on!
撑住
Look out!
小心
Mr. Joy!
乔伊先生
- We have to cut away the topgallants! - Topgallants away!
- 我们要割掉上层帆 - 上层帆要放掉
We have to get her upright!
我们要让船直立
You wish to see me, sir?
船长 你想见我?
At six bells tomorrow,
明早7点
you will assemble the crew.
你把船员集合
Inform them that we will be returning to Nantucket for repairs.
宣布我们会回南塔克岛修船
You will then apologize to them for interfering with a captain's order,
你要向他们道歉 因抵触船长的命令
which nearly cost the lives of every man on this ship today.
造成今天差点害死所有船员
What?
什么?
I'll accept your resignation upon our return to port. That will be all.
我们一返回港口 我会接受你的辞职 就这样
- It was your order to set stunsails, sir. - That decision was sound.
- 是你下令要张开副帆 - 那是明智的决定
The men needed testing.
船员需要考验
- So you send them into a storm? - That...
- 所以把他们送入风暴? - 那是...
- That was unlucky. - No, it was bad seamanship.
- 运气不佳 - 不 是差劲的航海术
And blaming misfortune is just plain weakness.
还有怪罪厄运简直是软弱
Damn your impertinence!
去你的无礼
Do you know who you're speaking to?
知道你在跟谁说话吗?
My name is Captain George Pollard. Pollard!
我是乔治波拉德船长 波拉德
And you, Mr. Chase, no matter how many whale pins you may have on your lapel,
而你 契斯先生 无论你的翻领上有多少饰针
are nothing more than the son of a farmer
你只不过是农家子弟
who's managed to bully his way into an officer's tunic.
老爸虚张声势肖想升官
Now get out.
给我出去
To return to port without a single barrel of oil would be a mistake, sir.
没带任何鱼油返航非明智之举
And not behoove a man whose name is Pollard.
不配姓波拉德的人
Or Chase, for that matter.
也不配姓契斯的人
And the best thing for both of us would be to work all hours God sends us,
我们两人的最好对策 就是拚死拚活
fill this ship with oil and be home inside a year
一年内满戴鲸油而归
and rid of one another as quickly as possible.
就能尽快摆脱对方
Trust me, I am every bit as desirous of that as you.
相信我 我跟你一样巴不得如此
Of course, that is a captain's decision.
当然那是船长的决定
They were like an ill-married couple.
他们像是一对怨偶
An ill-married couple will tolerate each other, Mr. Melville.
怨偶会互相容忍
But an ill-married couple can also bring down a ship.
但也会使船翻覆
Are you married, Mr. Melville?
梅尔维尔先生 你结婚了吗?
I am.
是的
God have mercy on you.
天佑你
First child on the way, too.
第一个孩子也即将出生
So, does your good wife know that you've brought all you have in the world here tonight
那你的贤妻知道 今晚你带着所有财产
and given it to a stranger?
来给一个陌生人?
No, sir.
不知道
You're full of surprises, aren't you?
你令人好不意外呀
So,
那么
the Essex did not return to port.
艾塞克斯号没有返航?
She did not.
没有
She continued out to sea.
继续航向大海
Yes, she did.
没错
And before long, we heard that call that all whalemen pray for.
过不久 我们听到所有猎鲸人 祈求的呼唤
"Blows."
喷水柱声
Blows!
喷水柱了
To windward! There she blows!
迎向上风 鲸鱼在喷水柱了
Right or sperm, Mr. Ramsdell?
兰司岱先生 露脊鲸或抹香鲸?
Sperm whales they are!
是抹香鲸
There go the flukes!
露出尾巴了
Mr. Chase! Hoist and swing boats.
契斯先生 把小艇放到海上
All hands! All hands on deck!
集合 全员到甲板
All hands on deck!
全员到甲板
Away the boats.
放下小艇
Lower away!
继续放
Straight! Crack them backbones.
直行 使劲划
Aye, sir!
遵命
Give way all. Spring those oars till your arms fall off.
全速 划到手断也要划
There they breach!
鲸鱼跳出水了
Thataway, boys! Full pressure!
那个方向 全力冲刺
Aye, sir!
遵命
Come on! Put your back into it.
加油 拚命划
Pull! Pull like a vengeance!
用力划 死命划
There she blows!
喷水柱了
That's a calf.
是幼鲸
That's the calf?
那是幼鲸?
That's the cow.
那是母鲸
And that's our boy! That's the money.
那才是我们的公鲸 要发财了
Nickerson, push!
尼可森 快划
Sorry, sir.
抱歉 先生
Forty-barreler?
40桶?
Fifty.
50桶
Oh, he's a buster!
它会打破纪录
Bite the oars, lads.
抓紧船桨 大伙儿
Blister your goddamn lungs!
豁出去了
Full pressure! Smartly, lads! Smartly!
全力冲刺 加把劲
Mind your oars!
注意船桨
Mr. Ramsdell, prepare the line.
兰司岱先生 绑好绳索
Aye, sir.
遵命
Mr. Lawrence, the first one's mine.
劳伦斯先生 第一只我来
Take me to the pretty spot.
带我到有利位置
Pull! Come on.
用力拉 加油
Stay on him.
跟紧它
You're on your first Nantucket sleigh ride, boy.
第一次坐南塔克雪橇兜风吧
Oh, my God!
我的天啊
Look at him! The most fearsome creature ever to live on this Earth.
瞧它 有史以来最令人生畏的动物
He sounds.
他潜入了
My hands!
我的手
LAWRENCE. We need to wet the line, Nickerson.
把绳索弄湿 尼可森
Give way, lads. Give way.
全速 全速
Got 140 fathoms of line left, Mr. Chase.
剩140噚的绳索 契斯先生
Eighty fathoms of line left, sir!
剩80噚的绳索
He's gonna pull us under!
它会把我们拉进海里
Matthew, I need your line!
马修 我需要绳索
Keep going!
继续
Peterson, give me the line.
彼得森 给我绳索
Aye, sir.
遵命
Give me that line, Mr. Peterson.
给我绳索 彼得森先生
We're down to 60 fathoms of line left, sir!
只剩60噚的绳索
Twenty fathoms, Mr. Chase.
20噚 契斯先生
Tie it off!
绑在一起
Safe!
绑紧了
Go!
放绳
- Peterson, lay out. - Aye, sir.
- 彼得森 你掌舵 - 遵命
How many fathoms can he go?
还剩多少噚?
70 fathoms left, sir.
剩70噚
No, no, no, wait.
不行 等等
Owen!
欧文
No, no! Not yet! Don't touch that line!
不行 还不行 别碰那条绳索
Down to 50 fathoms, sir.
只剩50噚
Owen, God damn it!
欧文 该死
I said don't touch it!
我说过别碰
30 fathoms left, Mr. Joy.
剩30噚 乔伊先生
Ten fathoms left, sir!
剩10噚
Backwater!
倒桨
Push!
划桨
Chimney's afire!
鲸鱼喷血了
Afire!
喷血了
Hurry it along, lads.
动作快 大伙儿
God! Get out, you bastards.
天啊 出来 混蛋
Blubber in the Oil. Smell that, boys!
炼成鲸油了 闻闻看
That's us making money!
是钱的味道
Get out of there, you sons of bitches.
快出来 王八蛋
- There, you got it? - There's not a chance.
- 还有搞头吗? - 没望了
- How's it looking? - It's not good.
- 还行吗? - 不乐观
That's it.
就这样了
Mr. Chase, sir.
契斯先生
Yeah?
什么事?
That's all of it, sir. We can't get any more out.
只有这样 捞不出更多了
That's the gold in there, boys. Come on, keep digging.
里面才是精华 快继续挖
We're too big to wriggle down there.
我们块头太大挤不进去
Then find someone who can.
那找下得去的人
Nickerson! Come here, boy.
尼可森 过来
Hey! I said come here.
别躲 我叫你过来
Climb on into him.
爬进去
Come on, Thomas.
快点 汤玛斯
What's in there is worth a hell of a lot more than what they're boiling down.
里面的鲸蜡 比他们提炼的鲸油值钱多了
Sir! I can't, I'm...
先生 我做不到
I'm sorry. I can't.
抱歉 我做不到
You get down there, or I'll have you sleep down there.
下去 否则就让你睡里面
You best put that between your teeth, boy.
你最好咬住这个
Stinks worse than the devil's asshole down there.
下面比粪坑还臭
Thanks.
谢谢
Sorry.
歹势
Here, Nickerson, take my pillow with you.
尼可森 我的枕头借你
Down you go.
下去吧
A man gets to know himself down there.
人在里面会认清自己
They ever send you into a whale's head?
你曾被塞入鲸鱼头吗?
No.
没有
I was spared.
我逃过一劫
Well, that's where the treasure is.
里面才是宝藏
I'll never forget that first bull.
我永生难忘第一只公鲸
Forty-seven barrels. 'Course, the happiness was short-lived.
47桶 但好景不常
- The waters there had all been fished out? - That they had.
- 那里的水域因滥捕没鲸鱼了? - 没错
So, we headed further out.
所以 我们得继续前行
Yeah. Took us a month to round the Horn.
所以 我们花一个月抵达合恩角
Left the South Atlantic behind with a sliver of hope
抛下南大西洋 抱着一丝希望
that things could change for the better.
期望情况会好转
But making the Pacific didn't improve our lot.
但到达太平洋 并没有改善我们的运气
Whale sightings were too damn scarce.
几乎看不到鲸鱼
After nearly a year at sea,
在海上将近一年后
the temperaments of our captain and first mate grew more strained.
船长和大副的关系愈来愈紧张
Captain Pollard spent most days and nights in his cabin,
波拉德船长整日待在他的房间
afraid to look his crew in the eye.
害怕看到船员的眼神
Our hold was almost empty.
我们的库存几乎空了
And to gaze upon our paltry efforts
看着我们徒劳的努力
only served as a reminder
只是提醒着大家
that we were a long way from going home.
我们离家愈来愈远了
No, no. I don't talk that talk. Speak English.
不 我不会说那种语言 说英语
Offer me more.
给我多点钱
Here, sir. This, Nantucket whale oil.
这是南塔克的鲸油
- Ain't no skinny hog worth more than that. - More!
- 瘦猪哪要这么贵 - 多点钱
Capitan. Excuse me. The locals told me your voyage was waylaid, sir.
船长 打扰了 当地人说你们航行时遭受攻击
Captain George Pollard. The Essex.
乔治波拉德船长
Capitan Clemente Pelaez, the Santa Maria.
克莱门佩雷兹船长 圣塔玛莉亚号
Would you buy a colleague a drink?
愿意请同行喝一杯吗?
No, no.
我不用
Bad luck? How far out?
运气差 是吧? 航行多远?
Far enough for only a fool to go.
远到只有笨蛋会去的地方
How far would that be?
那是多远?
A thousand leagues along the equator.
沿着赤道1000里格
The Offshore Grounds.
外海渔场
Were there whales there?
那里有鲸鱼吗?
More than you've ever dreamed.
多不胜数
Hundreds. Fields of flukes far as the eye can see.
几百只 一望无际的鲸鱼
Could have filled up 3,000 barrels in the space of a day.
一天内就可能装满3000桶
What do you mean, "could have"?
可能是什么意思?
If it weren't for that demon.
要不是那只魔鬼
A whale.
一只巨鲸
White as alabaster. Hundred feet long.
白得像大理石 身长100尺
Sent six of my crew to their graves.
杀死我六名船员
And the rest of us, something to remember him by.
还让我们幸存者忘不了它
Now, this white whale, did he dance a jig and pick your pocket as well?
这只白鲸也会跳舞和扒窃吗?
Gracias.
谢了
You believe that?
你们相信?
If we set sail now,
如果我们现在启航
catch the south easterlies at their best time and fill our belly, we could be home in six months.
趁机赶上的南半球东风 就能大丰收 半年后就能回家
What say you, Mr. Chase?
契斯先生 你说呢?
No need to endure our predicament for a moment longer than necessary.
不必再度日如年 忍受困境
Amen to that.
我同意
Amen.
同意
Greed took hold of our captain and first mate.
贪婪吞噬了我们的船长和大副
So we headed out.
于是我们出发
A thousand leagues along the equator.
沿着赤道1000里格
Where knowledge ended,
知识的终点
speculation began.
就是臆测的起点
That's where the whales had gone to hide.
那是鲸鱼的藏身处
As far from man as they could possibly go.
远到人类不可能到达
But we hunted them down.
但我们猎捕它们
Centuries before, sailors feared sailing off the edge of the Earth.
几世纪前 水手害怕驶离地球的边缘
But we were headed for the edge of sanity.
我们却逼近理智的边缘
Trust gave way to doubt.
信任被怀疑取代
Hope to blind superstition.
希望幻灭成迷信
Captain, the men are talking.
船长 船员在闲言闲语
That's what men do.
那是人之常情
They aren't happy with your decision to sail out this far.
他们不满意您决定航行这么远
Well, did you correct them? Did you remind them of our purpose to fill this ship with whale oil,
你有纠正他们吗? 提醒他们我们志在满载鲸油
and if the whales are 1,000 leagues out, that that is where we will go?
如果鲸鱼远在1000里格外 我们就要去那么远
Cousin, please.
表哥 拜托你
This is madness.
这太疯狂了
You have let yourself be influenced by that man. You must turn this ship back.
你被那个人洗脑了 你必须返航
I suggest you go back down, reassure the men,
我建议你回去安抚他们
be a leader
当个领导者
and don't ever, ever abuse the privilege of family with me again.
也绝对别再跟我滥用家族特权
Mr. Coffin.
柯芬先生
What is it?
怎么了?
Listen.
仔细听
Mr. Chase?
契斯先生?
I see some white water.
我看到白色浪花
- Where? - Portside!
- 哪里? - 左舷
- We're away! - Portside, Captain!
- 准备行动 - 左舷 船长
- Where are they? - You see anything?
- 鲸鱼在哪里? - 有看到动静?
Lower away!
放下小艇
The devil take the Mexican grounds!
那个魔鬼游向墨西哥渔场了
Peak oars!
船桨离水
Give it to him, Mr. Chappel!
投掷鲸叉 查普尔先生
Stick him, man! Stick him!
刺它 刺它
Dead ahead, Peterson!
就在前方 彼得森
Don't let him chew your oars, boys.
别让他咬到船桨
Back to it.
继续追
The whale?
那只巨鲸?
Yes.
对
So it's true?
所以是真的?
Too much is true.
大多是真的
Get it up!
起来
Full pressure!
全力冲刺
Mr. Bond!
邦德先生
Back the foreyard, lower the tackle!
撑住前桅下帆 降下索具
Aye, sir!
遵命
Here she comes, Peterson. Now, now!
鲸鱼靠近 彼得森 现在
Mr. Lawrence, take us leeward, head us straight for the school.
劳伦斯先生 转向背风 直接驶向鲸鱼群
Aye, sir.
遵命
Hot tar, sir.
热焦油
We'll find him.
我们会找到他的
We're boat to black skin.
旁边有鲸鱼
Beach us on her!
船压上去
She's ours, men!
抓到了
What was that, Mr. Lawrence?
劳伦斯先生 怎么回事?
Mr. Chase!
契斯先生
God damn it.
该死
Find Mr...
找劳伦斯...
Mr. Easton!
伊斯顿先生
Get Mr. Lawrence to man the pumps!
找劳伦斯先生来操作帮浦
Where is he?
它在哪里?
Port bow!
左舷船头
Get me the biggest irons we have.
给我最大支的鲸叉
He wants a fight?
他想一决高下
Never seen a whale do that.
从没看过鲸鱼会挑衅
Mr. Lawrence, take the wheel. Mr. Ramsdell, secure the other end of the line to the foremast.
劳伦斯 由你掌舵 兰司岱 把绳索另一端绑在前桅
Aye, sir.
遵命
As I live and breathe, he's mine.
只要我活着 他就是我的
- Cut the line! - Look out!
- 斩断 - 小心
- Captain! - What?
- 船长 - 什么?
The Essex! She's listing.
艾塞克斯号倾斜了
Turn this boat around!
小艇调头
- Help me! Mr. Joy! - Nickerson!
- 救我 乔伊先生 - 尼可森
- Here! Give me your hand! - Help!
- 手给我 - 救命
Nickerson!
尼可森
Mr. Chase!
契斯先生
A whale, sir. It stove the ship.
是一只白鲸 它把船撞破了
What?
什么?
We lost Easton and Sanborn.
伊斯顿和萨伯恩丧命了
The pumps are useless, sir.
帮浦没用
Prepare to abandon ship.
准备弃船
We can't row our way home.
我们划不回家
We'll have to strip her of her sails and jimmy-rig something.
拆下风帆 凑合着用
Gather as much food and water as you can carry.
尽量收集食物和饮水
We're gonna need all the fresh water you can find.
找出所有干净的水备用
Nickerson, you grab as much as you can. Barz, come with me.
尼可森 尽量拿 巴齐 跟我来
Sweet Lord!
老天
First, the sails, then the provisions.
先拿风帆和粮食
Get as much food as you can carry, lad.
食物尽量多拿
Make haste, boys!
动作快
Nickerson, there are more casks in steerage.
尼可森 统舱有更多水桶
Got it?
拿稳了?
Hardtack is dry. Move sprightly, gentlemen.
干粮没弄湿 加快速度 各位
Lower away!
降下风帆
- Take those tack lines. - Up aloft!
- 拿走角索 - 小心上面
- Lower away! Bring it down! - Mr. Cole, get that yard down.
- 降下风帆 - 柯勒先生 把帆桁拿下来
Bring it down. Keep it coming!
继续拆下来
Hold off!
拿稳
Come on, Nickerson!
快点 尼可森
Get those sails!
拿那些风帆
There you go.
契斯的小艇
Get that yard down!
把帆桁拿下来
We need the sails. Not enough water.
我们需要风帆 水也不够
Get the barrels, now!
快拿桶子
Strip that rigging!
拆掉索具
More fresh water! More hardtack! Come on!
拿更多干净的水和干粮 快点
I can see more casks in the steerage!
统舱能看到更多水桶
Benjamin! Quick! Come on!
班哲明 快抓住
- Give me your hand! - Get him up.
- 手给我 - 拉他上来
I got you.
我抓紧你了
Hardtack!
干粮
Come on! Move it!
快点 赶快
Step lively, Mr. Nickerson!
脚步快 尼可森先生
Gotta get away from the oil!
要远离鲸油
She's going down! She's listing!
船要沉了 倾斜了
Where's Owen? Nickerson, where is Mr. Chase?
欧文在哪里? 尼可森 契斯先生在哪里?
He was just here, sir.
他刚才还在
Come on, hurry up!
快点 赶快
Owen!
欧文
- Mr. Chase! - We gotta shove off!
- 契斯先生 - 赶快闪人
Come on, now, boys!
快点 大伙儿
Oil on deck!
甲板上有鲸油
- Captain! - Mr. Chase!
- 船长 - 契斯先生
Mr. Chase, sir!
契斯先生
Owen!
欧文
Where is the first mate?
大副在哪里?
She's gonna blow!
船要爆炸了
- Owen! - We gotta move!
- 欧文 - 要走了
No, wait! Wait!
不 等等
Mr. Chase, sir!
契斯先生
There he is! There he is! There he is!
他在那里 他来了
Move that!
移开
Mr. Chase, sir. Here!
契斯先生 这里
Get ahold, now. We got you.
抓住 抓到你了
- Sir. - You're all right now, Mr. Chase.
- 先生 - 你没事了 契斯先生
Going fishing, are we?
要去捕鱼吗?
Clean and load it, Mr. Joy.
清理利用 乔伊先生
Back away, or she'll take us down with her.
后退 不然我们会被波及
Captain.
船长
What about our provisions?
粮食怎么分配?
Two ounces of hardtack a day per man.
每人一天2盎司的干粮
And half a cup of water.
还有半杯水
Hey, man, we can't live on that.
剩那丁点哪能活
Not for more than a few days.
顶多撑几天
It's he.
是它
Yeah, it's him, all right.
对 是它没错
You don't fool me, Mr. Chase.
别耍我 契斯先生
Mr. Coffin?
柯芬先生
That right?
是吗?
You put us here. You know you put us here.
你害我们沦落这般田地 你心知肚明
- Hey! Put it down! - Mr. Coffin, put the pistol down.
- 放下 放下 - 柯芬先生 把枪放下
Say you're scared!
承认你很害怕
- What are you doing? - Mr. Coffin, put the pistol down.
- 你在干嘛? - 柯芬先生 把枪放下
You know what happens when the food and water runs out?
你知道食物和饮水耗尽 是什么结果?
Do as the captain says, Coffin!
听船长的话 柯芬
- I just wanna see the landsman scared. - Mr. Coffin, put the pistol down.
- 我只想看那个内陆人害怕 - 柯芬 把枪放下
- That's an order! - Do as the captain says! Now.
- 这是命令 - 快听船长的话
Say it!
快说
- Henry. - Say it!
- 亨利 - 快说
Henry!
亨利
Put the pistol down.
把枪放下
Put it down.
放下
So east it was.
于是我们往东
Back in the direction we'd come.
反方向回去
Though only the sun and compass told us so.
只能靠太阳和罗盘判断
All directions looked the same.
所有方向看起来都一样
Our hope was to catch the Westerlies to Easter Island.
我们希望赶上西风到复活岛
A journey of 3,000 miles.
3000哩的旅程
In 12 days, we have drifted south.
我们往南漂流了12天
Six degrees latitude.
纬度6度
We're not one mile closer to Easter Island.
一点也没接近复活岛
We stayed in the same place.
我们在原地打转
We are cursed.
我们被诅咒了
We'll make up for it when we catch the variables.
赶上风向变时 我们会加快进度
We'll catch them.
我们会赶上的
Chappel!
查普尔
You've got him, Captain!
你救回他了 船长
Mr. Joy, the halyard's jammed!
乔伊先生 吊索卡住了
Mr. Joy!
乔伊先生
You all right, Mr. Joy?
乔伊先生 你没事吧?
Grab the tiller!
握住舵柄
- Grab it! - Matthew!
- 握住 - 马修
Get that sail down!
把风帆降下
Matthew. Hey, what happened? What happened?
马修 怎么了? 怎么回事?
Owen. What are you doing here?
欧文 你在这里干嘛?
- Let me take a look. - No, no, no.
- 让我看一下 - 不要
Lay still. Let me look.
躺好 让我看一下
- Owen, I'm fine. All right. - Just relax. Relax. Let me take a look.
- 欧文 我没事 - 冷静 让我看一下
- I'm fine! - I know. I know. I just wanna take a look.
- 我没事 - 我知道 我只想看一眼
I banged my head. Just a scratch, all right?
我撞到头 只是擦伤 好吗?
- Just a scratch. - Give him some water.
- 只是擦伤 - 给他一些水
I don't need any water!
我不需要水
Give him some goddamn water!
快给他一些水
No, no, no. I don't need water. I'm fine.
不用 我不需要水 我很好
Take that. Take it.
快喝下
Hey. I got you, I got you.
我帮你 我帮你
You're all right. You're all right.
你没事 你没事
Hey! What're you all looking at? I'm fine.
你们看什么劲? 我很好
Captain Pollard. Fit as a fiddle.
波拉德船长 我健康极了
Fit as a goddamned fiddle. You hear me?
健康毙了 听到没?
- Owen. - Yeah.
- 欧文 - 怎样?
I'm fine. All right? I'm fine!
我没事 好吗? 我没事
- You're a tough son of a bitch. - Thank you. I'm fine.
- 你有够顽固 - 谢了 我很好
Get out of here.
快走开
He's good.
他没事
Let's go.
走吧
Why waste water on a dead man?
干嘛浪费水给快死的人?
Them two men have known each other,
他们是好朋友
sailed together since childhood.
从小就一起出航
Now, tell me, could you sit there and watch your own brother die?
告诉我 你能袖手旁观 看自己的兄弟死掉吗?
Simply a matter of numbers, Mr. Chappel.
我只是实事求是 查普尔先生
There's not enough for all of us.
大家都不够喝
Why waste water on a dead man?
干嘛浪费水给快死的人?
Why waste water on...
干嘛浪费水...
Why waste water? Why waste?
干嘛浪费水? 干嘛浪费?
Why waste water on a dead man?
干嘛浪费水给快死的人?
Mr. Nickerson?
尼可森先生
Why waste water...
干嘛浪费水?
You all right, sir?
你没事吧?
I cannot.
我办不到
Cannot what?
办不到什么?
No, you...
不 你...
You have enough. More than enough.
你知道够了 太多了
But, sir, we've come so far.
但我们谈到这节骨眼了
We have come to an end.
我们要谈到结局
We have an agreement, sir.
我们说好了
Take the money and leave! The devil's bargain.
拿钱离开 魔鬼的交易
No, sir. The devil loves unspoken secrets.
不 先生 魔鬼喜欢不可告知的秘密
Especially those that fester in a man's soul.
尤其是腐蚀人心的秘密
What's yours?
那你的秘密呢?
I am not a great writer.
我不是个伟大作家
I am not Hawthorne.
我不是霍桑
But from my first hearing of it,
但从我第一次听到这个故事
this tale has haunted me.
它就萦绕在我心头
It consumes me.
挥之不去
I fear if I do not write it,
我怕如果不把它写出来
then I should never write again.
我就该永远封笔
What else?
还有呢?
I fear if I do write it,
我怕如果我写出来
that it will not be as good as it should be.
却辜负了该有的杰作
Continue the story, sir.
请继续这个故事
For the both of us.
为我们两人着想
Pass that down.
传过去
Thank you, sir.
谢谢
We thank you, Lord, for this is our food.
我们感谢主 赐予我们食物
I'm sorry.
抱歉
For life and health, and every good.
赐予生命 健康 各种良善
Let all manner to...
让所有行为...
Land. Land!
陆地 陆地
- Land! Land! - Land!
- 陆地 陆地 - 陆地
Land!
陆地
Oars! Give way! Give way!
划桨 全速 全速
Oars! Now! Give way!
划桨 快点 全速
Row!
快划
- I saw it, Mr. Chase. - That you did, boy.
- 是我发现的 契斯先生 - 多亏你了
Hold fast. Hold fast! Hold fast!
停住 停住 停住
Mr. Chase, sir. What is it?
契斯先生 怎么了?
Mr. Chase! What the devil is it? Why have you stopped?
契斯先生 搞什么鬼? 干嘛停?
He's been following us!
它一直跟踪我们
What is he talking about?
他在说什么?
There's nothing out there, Mr. Chase! There ain't nothing out there, sir!
海上毫无动静 什么都没有啊
Sir, what are you doing?
先生 你在干嘛?
Brace! Brace! Brace!
抓稳 抓稳 抓稳
No!
糟了
Where is he?
它在哪里?
This could be Ducie Island.
这可能是丢昔岛
Without a map, compass or quadrant, there's no way to be certain.
没有地图 罗盘或四分仪无法确定
We will keep fires going night and day.
我们日以继夜升着火
Hope a passing ship catches sight of our smoke.
希望有经过的船会看到烟
This is what I wanted you to see.
我要你们看这景象
They've been here a long time, no doubt.
他们肯定在这里很久了
Waiting for a ship.
等船来救援
But no ship came.
但没有船来
No ship is going to come.
没有船会来的
If we stay, we die.
我们待着就是等死
How long do you think it'll take the tropic birds to stop coming here once they see their eggs eaten?
想想鸟儿看到蛋被我们吃了 有多久不会再回来?
It's a privilege to know the moment of one's death in advance,
事先知道死期是恩赐
be able to prepare for it.
这样才能做好准备
Curse to be so far from home
我们不幸远离家园
without a chance to say goodbyes, without a chance to make peace,
没有机会道别与和解
without a chance to settle the scores.
没有机会化解宿怨
Then let us at least settle those between us, Captain.
那起码化解我们俩的宿怨吧 船长
Captain of what?
什么船长?
The Essex was lost through no fault of yours.
艾塞克斯号毁坏不是你的错
- I was as much to blame for... - You are not the captain.
- 要怪就怪我 - 你不是船长
But you were born to do this job.
但你天生是船长的料
I was just born into it.
我只是平白继承家业
What do we do, do you think, George?
乔治 你想我们该怎么做?
And what offense did we give God to upset him so?
我们到底是哪里触怒了上帝?
The only creature to have offended God here is the whale.
只有那只白鲸触怒了上帝
Not us?
不是我们?
In our arrogance, our greed, look where we find ourselves.
自大和贪婪使我们落入这种下场
We are supreme creatures made in God's own likeness.
人类是上帝以自身模样 创造出的最高等生物
Earthly kings
尘世之王
whose business it is to circumnavigate the planet bestowed to us.
其使命便是环航赐予我们的星球
To bend nature to our will.
依我们的意志操控大自然
You really feel like an earthly king after everything that we've been through?
经历这一切后 你还自诩为尘世之王?
We're nothing. We're...
我们无足轻重
We're specks. And dust.
微不足道 一文不值
We sail into the sun at dawn.
我们日出时往东
If we are to die,
如果我们会死
then with God's grace,
那在上帝的慈悲下
let us die as men.
让我们死得有尊严
Are we ready, Mr. Weeks?
卫克斯先生 准备好了?
Aye, sir.
是 先生
Mr. Chappel? Mr. Wright?
查普尔先生 莱特先生
I can't do it, sir.
我做不到
Me, Wrights and Weeks,
我 莱特和卫克斯
we're staying.
我们要留下来
You ready to go, Matthew?
马修 准备走了?
- I'll give you a hand. Here, you gotta get up. - No, there's no point.
- 我扶你起来 - 毫无意义
- You hear me? - No, we're going home. We're going home.
- 听到没? - 我们要回家
There's no point.
毫无意义
Just go.
你走吧
God damn it, Matthew.
该死 马修
It's all right.
没关系
Well, I'll send a boat for you the minute we get back.
我一回去就会派船来接你
Then we'll play cards back in Nantucket, all right?
我们会回南塔克岛打牌 好吗?
Yeah.
好
- It's a deal. - Good.
- 一言为定 - 好
You want me to open that for you?
要我帮你打开吗?
I think I'll manage.
我会搞定
If it comes to that.
如果不得不如此
God be with you, brother.
上帝与你同在 兄弟
Yeah, and you.
你也是
Brother Peterson?
彼得森兄弟
Y'all coming with us?
你要跟我们来吗?
Mr. Peterson. Why don't you come in our boat with Mr. Bond here?
彼得森先生 来我们的船跟邦德先生一道吧
Where... Where is he?
他在哪里?
Pollard?
波拉德?
Mr. Lawrence. Mr. Lawrence, wake up.
劳伦斯先生 醒醒
Where's the other boat gone?
另一艘船去哪里了?
Pollard!
波拉德
- Captain Pollard! - Captain Pollard!
- 波拉德船长 - 波拉德船长
Captain Pollard, sir!
波拉德船长
- Pollard. - Captain!
- 波拉德 - 船长
Pollard!
波拉德
What's the matter?
怎么了?
Benjamin. What are you doing?
班哲明 你在干嘛?
He's dead.
他死了
Putting him overboard, sir.
给他海葬
Look at me. Look at me, Benjamin.
看着我 看着我 班哲明
No right-minded sailor discards what might yet save him.
理智的水手不会丢弃救命工具
Listen to me, boy. Listen to me.
听我说 小子
He can help us.
他能救我们
My God. My heavenly king.
上帝 天上君主
Sweetness is the power of his grace.
和蔼是其恩典的力量
With longing eyes,
望眼欲穿
thy creatures await on thee for daily food.
祢的创造物等待祢赐予每日食物
My soul is dead.
我的灵魂已死
So it was decided.
于是我们决定了
We prepared the body.
我们把尸体剖开
We removed the organs.
切除器官
Separated his limbs from his body
分开四肢和躯体
and cut all the flesh from the bones.
刮下骨头上的所有肉
After which,
之后...
we closed the body
我们组合尸骨
and we sewed it up
缝起来
as decently as we could
尽可能体面地
and committed it to the sea.
献给大海
We ate the heart first.
我们先吃心脏
You judge me.
你在批判我
No.
没有
There.
终于
It is done.
我说出来了
It is out.
真相大白了
And you've never told anyone?
你从没告诉任何人?
No.
没有
Not even your wife?
甚至你妻子?
Do you think she could ever love me
若她得知我罪不容诛的恶行
if she knew the abominations I had committed?
你想她还会爱我吗?
Yes. She would.
会 她会
And if you had told me the story when we met,
如果我们相遇时 你告诉我这个故事
I would still wear your ring today.
我今天还是会戴着你的婚戒
The strength of that boy still lives in you.
那男孩的力量还活在你心里
I see that.
我看得到
Even if you don't.
即使你看不见
You can finish your story now, my love.
说完你的故事吧 亲爱的
Hey, sit up.
坐起来
Listen,
听着
put your head back.
头躺回去
Look, we still got a few drops of water left.
我们还剩几滴水
Don't you quit on me. We're going home.
别放弃 我们会回家
Do you have a family back home, Mr. Chase?
你在家乡有家人吗 契斯先生?
Yeah, I have a wife.
有 我有妻子
Yes, and a son or a daughter.
还有一个儿子或女儿
Very well.
好吧
Captain.
船长
We will draw again.
重抽一次
We will do no such thing.
绝不可以
Mr. Ramsdell,
兰司岱先生
you will assume command of this vessel.
由你指挥这艘船
Cousin, will you?
表弟 麻烦了
You're our... You're our captain. The men need you.
你是我们的船长 船员需要你
The men will be fine.
他们会很好的
Please.
拜托
Please. Please.
拜托 拜托
- Henry. - Let us draw again.
- 亨利 - 重抽一次
It is an order.
这是命令
If you cannot do it, pass the pistol to another man.
如果下不了手 把枪交给其他人
Henry, no, no, no!
亨利 不要
You gotta help me, kid. You gotta help me.
你要帮我 你要帮我
We were weeks in the doldrums.
我们在无风带几周了
That part of the Pacific is more desert than ocean.
太平洋的那一隅 像是沙漠而非海洋
The sun beating down.
暴露在烈阳下
My fear.
我很恐惧
All I could think about
我最怕想到
was that everyone would die, and I'd be the last left alive.
大家死了 只剩我活着
And as best Mr. Chase could tell, we were still 800 miles from land.
契斯先生尽力推断 我们仍离陆地800哩
Mr. Chase.
契斯先生
Captain Pollard.
波拉德船长
I am happy to see you.
很高兴见到你
Been very little happiness in our survival.
我们能存活称不上高兴
Or in ours, sir.
我们也是
Barzillai?
巴齐莱呢?
The third boat?
第三艘船呢?
They've, uh...
他们...
They've been gone for days. I'm afraid they're lost, sir.
他们不见几天了 恐怕是失踪了
Mr. Chase, you have the best position.
契斯先生 你在最佳位置
It's just a whale.
只是只鲸鱼
He's there! Throw the lance!
它在那里 投掷矛枪
Throw it!
快投
Throw it! Throw the lance!
快投 投掷矛枪
Come on.
来啊
Throw it!
快投
Kill it! He's there! Throw the lance!
杀死它 它在那里 投掷矛枪
Why didn't you kill it?
你为什么不杀它?
You're a damn fool.
你有够傻
Currents drew us apart
水流拆散我们
and that was the last we would see of Captain Pollard's whale boat.
那是最后一次 我们看到波拉德船长的捕鲸艇
A boat!
有船
Broad on the port bow!
左舷船头的顺风处
May God have mercy.
愿主饶恕
Mr. Chase.
契斯先生
Father!
父亲
Don't leave me, Father!
别丢下我 父亲
Mr. Chase.
契斯先生
Sir, look. Look, sir.
先生 你看
look.
你看
Wake up, Mr. Chase! Here, wake up!
醒醒 契斯先生 快醒醒
Please wake up, sir, there's land.
拜托醒醒 是陆地
Mr. Chase, look.
契斯先生 你看
We were rescued there,
我们获救了
off the island of Mas Afuera, Chile,
在智利马斯阿富埃拉岛的外海
90 days after the sinking of the Essex.
在艾塞克斯号沉船的90天后
They gave us some old clothes. Fed us, too.
当地人给我们一些旧衣跟食物
It was hard to eat at first. Strange.
说来奇怪 一开始难以下咽
They looked after us as best they could
他们尽力照顾我们
till we found a ship that would carry us home.
直到我们找到能载我们回家的船
That voyage took another three months.
返航又花了3个月
It looked like the whole island turned out to see us return.
看来全岛的人都来迎接我们
But there were no cheers.
但没有欢呼
Only silence.
只有沉默
They looked at us like we were
他们看着我们像是见到...
apparitions,
鬼魂
phantoms.
幽灵
We'd said nothing of the details of our survival to anyone,
我们没跟任何人说 我们如何存活的细节
but I wondered if they somehow knew of our privations.
但我怀疑他们猜到我们如何维生
Maybe they were just curious.
也许他们很好奇
Oh, my God!
我的天啊
I promised, didn't I?
我保证过 对吧?
Oh, God.
天啊
Hi.
嗨
Hey, sweetie. Who's this?
嗨 小乖 这是谁?
Phoebe Ann.
翡柏安
Phoebe Ann Chase, huh?
翡柏安契斯?
This is Daddy.
这是爹地
Hey, sweetie.
嗨 小乖
It's your daddy.
是你的爹地
Oh, my God.
我的天啊
Of course, they couldn't leave him alone.
当然 他们不会放过他
Mr. Chase and his wife had scarcely walked a block towards home
契斯先生和妻子正走回家时
when he was stopped and made to return to the Maritime office.
他就被拦下送去海事处
There were business matters still in question.
还有商业问题要解决
So, to the matter.
针对这件事
Due to the significant loss of life and property on our voyage,
由于这一趟造成 重大的生命和财产损失
it seems there will be an inquiry.
似乎会有调查
And as captain and first mate, we will be expected to give an account of what happened.
身为船长和大副 我们势必要说明来龙去脉
Yes, of course.
当然
And having discussed this with the ship owners
我已经跟船主和家父
and my father,
讨论过这件事
it is clear that full disclosure will have ramifications.
显然据实公开会引发争议
Terrible ramifications for the whole industry.
造成全捕鲸业的严重分歧
That a whale brought down the Essex.
若说有只巨鲸撞沉艾塞克斯号
But it's the truth.
但这是事实
If the insurance houses and investors were to start worrying about
如果保险公司和投资者开始担心
sea monsters sinking ships,
有海怪会导致沉船
sailors drawing lots to survive...
水手靠抽签存活
We are in the oil business.
我们身在鲸油业
All of us.
我们所有人
And as in any business, the probability of success must always be greater than the risk incurred.
如同任何产业 若想成功获利 总是要蒙受高风险
So, what are you suggesting, George?
乔治 你在暗示什么?
That you say the ship ran aground.
你要说船是触礁
That's a lie.
那是谎言
And that the men that died, drowned.
还有船员是淹死
And that's another lie.
那也是谎言
- Think on it. They will make you captain. - Well, that pledge I already have in writing.
- 想清楚 他们会让你当上船长 - 那已经有书面承诺
Only on the condition you bring home a ship full of oil.
但条件是你满载鲸油而归
This way, it's guaranteed.
照做就有保证
You would be a wealthy man.
你会成为有钱人
The name Chase need no longer be a landsman's name, but an established name
契斯的姓氏就不再是内陆姓氏 而是公认的姓氏
that belongs among the great families of Nantucket.
会跻身南塔克岛的伟大家族
You want me to whitewash what happened for profit?
你们要我为了利益掩盖真相?
We are asking you to be pragmatic.
我们要求你务实
The Essex was stove by a white whale.
艾塞克斯号是被一只白鲸撞沉的
And those of us that survived in ill-equipped whaleboats had to commit abominations
我们幸存者在装备不良的捕鲸艇上 不得不丧尽天良
in order to survive.
以求生存
And, on our return, we're expected to spread barefaced lies
我们回来时却被强迫 散布公然的谎言
so that you, the ship owners of Nantucket,
好让你们这些南塔克岛的船主
might line your pockets and sleep well at night?
能口袋更深 夜夜好眠?
Well, I will not embroider the truth.
我不会粉饰真相
Nor should you, George.
你也不该 乔治
That last time I saw him...
我最后一次看到他
Mr. Chase, sir!
契斯先生
I couldn't find the right words to say what I wanted to.
我有话想说 却不知从何说起
Thomas.
汤玛斯
Perhaps there are no words.
也许尽在不言中吧
I'm gonna be on my way to Falmouth and...
我要去法尔茅斯 而...
It's...
这是...
It's been an honor, sir, to sail with you.
与您一起航行是我的荣幸
The honor's been mine, Mr. Nickerson.
我与有荣焉 尼可森先生
Here.
送你
Good luck out there, Thomas.
祝你好运 汤玛斯
And you, sir.
您也是
Next day, George Pollard was called before the inquiry.
隔天乔治波拉德被传唤接受调查
Gentlemen, Captain George Pollard.
各位 乔治波拉德船长
And all the important men in Nantucket were there.
南塔克岛的所有大人物都在场
It was a formality.
那只是个形式
Good day to you, Captain. Please sit down.
你好 船长 请坐
For the record, then...
请郑重声明
The Essex was stove by a white whale
艾塞克斯号是被一只白鲸撞沉
1,200 leagues west of Ecuador.
在厄瓜多尔以西1200里格
It was as if Owen Chase himself had spoken.
一如欧文契斯的主张
Told them the truth.
他揭露了真相
Captain Pollard's conscience was clear.
波拉德船长的神志很清明
But the inquiry was a sham.
但调查只是幌子
Pollard went out again,
波拉德再度出航
looking for the white whale.
寻找那只白鲸
He never found it.
他从没找到
He ran a second ship aground off Hawaii.
他在夏威夷外海二度触礁
Twice cursed.
两次诅咒
Never sailed again.
从此不再航行
And Owen Chase?
欧文契斯呢?
He was a man of his word.
他是守信的人
First, he sent a boat back to Ducie Island.
首先他派船回到丢昔岛
Mr. Joy had passed.
乔伊先生过世了
But the other three were, incredibly, still alive.
但其他三人奇蹟式生还
And then?
然后呢?
And then he packed up his family and moved to New Bedford.
他携家带眷搬到新贝德福特
Started over.
重振旗鼓
Became a merchant captain,
成为商船的船长
sailing on his own terms.
自主地航行
Well, you certainly got your money's worth, Mr. Melville.
你想必值回票价了 梅尔维尔先生
These February nights are the longest of the year.
一年中就二月的夜晚最漫长了
Well, you can both rest now.
你们都能休息了
Believe me,
相信我
I shall not be resting for some time.
我这阵子不可能休息了
Why?
为什么?
You got your story.
你有你要的故事了
You know, your plot. It's all there.
所有的情节你都记在笔记簿上了
Maybe it wasn't a plot I was after.
也许我追寻的不是情节
No. What, then?
不是 那是什么?
Something else you've given me tonight.
今晚你给我的意外收获
And what's that?
那是什么?
The courage to go where
那股勇气...
one does not want to go.
做出事不得已的事
Mr. Melville,
梅尔维尔先生
what you've heard, what I've told you,
你听到的一切 我所说的一切
will it all be of service to your book?
会全部写进你的书中吗?
It will be a work of fiction, Mr. Nickerson,
这会是虚构作品 尼可森先生
inspired by truth.
只是灵感来自真相
But I don't believe I'll feel the need to use all of it.
但我想没必要全部写进去
- Thank you. - Here.
- 谢谢 - 拿去
Take that with you.
拿回去吧
No. The money is for you. I insist.
不 我坚持你收下
I insist you keep it.
我坚持你留着
And I insist one person in this conversation is sober.
我坚持这场对话有人头脑清楚
So it's back to, uh...
那你要回...
Pittsfield, Massachusetts.
麻萨诸塞州的皮茨菲尔德
Well, good luck.
祝好运了
Thank you.
谢谢
You know,
对了
I heard a man from Pennsylvania drilled a hole in the ground recently
我听说最近宾夕法尼亚州 有人在地上钻个洞
and found oil.
发现了油
That can't be true.
不可能是真的吧
I heard it, too.
我也听说了
Oil from the ground.
来自陆地上的油
Fancy that.
异想天开